NICOLÁS PÉREZ

STATISTICIAN | DATA ANALYST | DATA SCIENTIST

CONTACT

NICOLÁS PÉREZ

nicolasp89@gmail.com (+31) 06 87 89 68 4*2*

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

DATA ANALYSIS

MICROSOFT EXCEL

PROGRAMMING IN R

GENERAL PROGRAMMING

MATHEMATICAL MODELING

OPERATIONS RESEARCH

SIMULATION

OPTIMIZATION

PERSONAL SKILLS

COMPUTER LANGUAGES

MATHEMATICS

RECURSIVENESS

TEAMWORK

TIME MANAGEMENT

MOTIVATED

FAST LEARNER

PROFESSIONAL

THOROUGH

BUSINESS UNDERSTANDING

CUSTOMER RELATIONS

RESULT ORIENTED

LOGIC THINKING

LANGUAGES

ENGLISH

SPANISH

FRENCH

DUTCH

PROFILE

Industrial Engineer and current master student in Methodology and Statistics in Utrecht University. I believe in the proper use of statistics and mathematical modeling to get relevant answers and insightful information in real world problems. I count with more than 4 years of professional experience in consulting in different fields and companies in Colombia and South America.

I am highly interested in continuous learning in professional and personal terms and I have excellent abilities in the use of analytical techniques. I have a particular passion for challenging situations and enjoy cooperating with different people to overcome them.

EDUCATION

MASTER IN SCIENCE CANDIDATE IN METHODOLOGY AND STATISTICS

Utrecht University, The Netherlands | 2016 - 2018

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN INDUSTRIAL ENGINEERING

Universidad de los Andes, Colombia | 2007 - 2012 Major Area: Operations Research - Minor Area: Finances

INTERNATIONAL HIGHSCHOOL DIPLOMA IN SWISS EDUCATION

Colegio Helvetia, Colombia | 2001 - 2007 Maturité Suisse

ACADEMIC EXPERIENCE

UTRECHT UNIVERSITY | 2016 - 2018

Programme advisory committee participation as student representative for the MSBBSS (Methodology and Statistics for the Behavioural, Biomedical and Social Sciences) programme.

BACHELOR RESARCH PROJECT | 2012

Building a competitiveness index with the use of Principal Component Analysis (PCA), based on the Global Competitiveness Index published by the World Economic Forum",

HIGHSCHOOL RESARCH PROJECT | 2007

Mathematical modeling of a fern's fractal growth

EXPERIENCE

CONSULTANT

IQuartil Ltda. | May 2015- Aug 2016

- Economic evaluation of the impact in transport costs of ship delays in loading ports through a Montecarlo simulation model in the largest coal mine in
- Colombia.
- Development of a VBA macro to perform K-means clustering in Excel files.
- Data base preparation and data analysis of a survey related to private and public transportation preferences and habits amongst the citizens of the city of Santa Marta (Colombia)
- Development of an alert and prediction model for attrition in the largest public higher-education provider in Colombia (SENA). Jointly developed with Microsoft
- Colombia.
- Business Accelerator and KPI design for SENA as defined in the Startegic Plan with Microsoft Colombia- Jointly developed with Microsoft Colombia

AWARDS AND DISTINCTIONS

OUTSTANDING RESULTS IN BACHELOR

4.15 / 5.0 GPA - 2012 5.0 / 5.0 score in research project

OUTSTANDING RESULTS IN HIGHSCHOOL

Best student of the class for two consecutive years (2005 - 2006 and 2006 - 2007)

OUTSTANDING RESULTS IN SWISS INTERNATIONAL DIPLOMA

One of the 3 best students to receive the International Highschool Diploma "Maturité

SOFTWARE

R

SPSS

STATA

CRYSTAL BALL

FLEXSIM

sQL

ADVANCED EXCEL

MICROSOFT AZURE STUDIO

LATEX

MARKDOWN

REFERENCES

DANIEL CUERVO

Partner at IQuartil Ltda. daniel.cuervo@iquartil.net (+571) 629 22 04

CAMILO DUQUE

CEO at Vatic Group - SDI Colombia camilo.duque@vaticgroup.com (+571) 317 892 93 95 • Survey design, implementation and data processing of a CAPI survey related to young mothers in lower socio-economic groups in the city of Cartagena

CONSULTANT AND PROJECT DIRECTOR

Vatic Group - SDI Colombia | May 2013- May 2015

- Active participation in more than 10 consulting projects on Operations Research for Supply Chain design and improvment in different companies in Colombia and Latin America
- Participation in transversal strategic projects in logistics that affects more than a single area in the company such as Distribution Center Design, Network Design, Decision Support Modeling, Simulation Studies, Investment Return Analysis, KPI design and Productivity Improvement Assessments
- Project director for the Strategic Project of Logistics Transformation for one of the most important alimentary product companies in Colombia. Responsible for customer relations, PMO labor and team management
- Statistical analysis for multiple purposes according to the specific requirements of each of the assessments (SQL queries, VBA macros, Excel modeling, FlexSim).
- Main analyst in distribution center design projects (including future operation modeling) in some of the most important companies in Colombia selling personal care products and footwear.

JUNIOR ANALYST

B.O.T. Concesiones de Gerencia | Dec 2012- Feb 2013

- Participation in different consulting projects with emphasis in educational services in Colombia such as a Fast assessment quantification of the VET (Vocational Education and Training) market size in Colombia, for evaluating the opportunity to enter into that market with a new company.
- Project analyst for the optimization of the scholarship calling process for doctorate and postgraduate studies in one of the main funding organizations in Colombia. The study was based on a specific framework which contemplated the practices and procedures used by the top leading study funding organizations worldwide.
- Participation in a Strategic Planning, Benchmarking and Market Analysis Project for one of the top 3 leading law firms in Colombia.

JUNIOR CONSULTANT

IQuartil Ltda. | Jan 2012- Sep 2012

- Statistical analysis and modeling for risk hedging related to price variations in different coffee grain varieties in Colombia for the largest food company in Colombia. Different tools and methodologies were included for the development of the mentioned models, such as: Financial Options & FOREX trade mechanisms, inventory optimization modeling, price-band negotiation models and decision trees, all of them based under time-series predictions for coffee prices in Colombia and the New York Market.
- Frozen food Market market-share analysis and evaluation for a foreign company interested in entering the Colombian market.
- Statistical survey analysis for the evaluation of the implementation of automatized pricing (taximeter) in taxis in Barranquilla.

NEW BUSINESS DEVELOPMENT CHIEF OFFICE INTERN

Vetra Exploración y Producción | Jun 2010 - Dec 2010

- Monte Carlo simulation modeling for the evaluation of the expected financial results for oil exploitation contracts in Kurdistan.
- Investment Portfolio valuation for different oil exploitation alternatives in Colombia.
- Optimization modeling for oil production and extraction in specific oil Wells in Colombia, based on the behavior of oil prices in Colombia in the previous years.
- Market share investment analysis for determining the best participation amount for the company in the construction and use of a public-private pipeline (Oleoducto Bicentenario) in Colombia. The valuation considered different uses of transport and their associated return over time.